MISSION 16 "IT'S JUST A JOKE."
（任務16 是搞笑哏）
Morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
You're early…
今天妳好早來啊…
Already?
已經開始顫抖了？
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
SHOW
（遞出）
What could she be so nervous to tell me?
她即使這麼緊張 也要告訴我的事情是什麼？
THE BEDBUG BUGGED THE BED.
（蓋棉被安眠唄）
Is this… code?
這是什麼暗號嗎？
What is it?
什麼意思啊？
"Yesterday, on TV they said humor is important for communication.
“昨天電視上說 和人交流時幽默很重要
So I wrote down a joke I heard recently."
於是我寫下了 最近覺得好笑的搞笑哏”
Recently?
“最近”？
Um, jokes like that work better in the right situation.
這類搞笑哏配合當下情境會比較好
-I ALMOST STEPPED IN A POODLE. -It is raining cats and dogs…
-（雨天撐傘魂飛破傘） -對喔，現在是梅雨季
I don't mean it wasn't funny.
我不是說不好笑喔
But with jokes,
但搞笑哏這種東西
it works better if you say them out loud.
還是要說出來比較有感覺
VIBRATE
（震動聲）
My phone?
電話？
What language do oranges speak? Mandarin.
鋁罐需要瀝乾
What's with all the dad jokes, Komi?!
妳為什麼這麼堅持要說冷笑話？
KOMI CAME BACK.
（古見同學回來了）
-HOW WERE THEY? -Should I say it?
-（好笑嗎？） -我可以老實說嗎？
Dad jokes just aren't funny. Should I tell her?
我可以老實跟她說 冷笑話一點都不好笑嗎？
Morning!
早安
I hate how damp and sticky this season is.
這個季節濕氣好重，真討厭
I'm saved.
救星來了
Now that I think of it.
對了
-HARPOON ON THE BOOM. -This sinister note was in my locker.
-我的鞋櫃裡有一張可疑紙條 -（水管由誰關？）
Another victim!
這裡也有受害人！
-TADANO EXPLAINS. -I see.
原來是這麼回事啊
I thought for sure it was an encoded death threat.
我還以為是寫成暗號的殺人預告呢
Alright Tadano.
好，只野同學
Show Komi how it's done!
你就示範給古見同學看看吧！
Huh?
什麼？
EXCITED
（期待）
She's waiting.
她好期待
I guess I'd better do it?
只能硬著頭皮上了嗎？
Puns about the wind… blow.
貓貓愛抓毛毛蟲
Terrible.
你太令人失望了
The same level as Komi.
和古見同學屬於同一等級
-W-WOW… -SPARKLE
（好厲害 閃亮）
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
Bear in mind, they only struggle to form connections.
不過需要注意的是 這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
MISSION 17 "IT'S JUST SHOPPING."
（任務17 去購物）
Hey Komi, where do you buy your clothes?
古見同學平常都在哪裡買衣服啊？
"You've never bought any?!"
“我沒買過”？
So… what do you do on your days off?
那假日時妳都做什麼？
-I DON'T GO OUT VERY MUCH, SO… -That's sad, Komi!
-（我幾乎不出門） -這樣太讓人悲傷了，古見同學
Alright. Let's go clothes shopping today!
那我們今天一起去買衣服吧！
TO THE STATION!
（去車站大樓！）
UM… I APPRECIATE THE THOUGHT, BUT…
（那個…謝謝你的好意，我很開心）
-THAT'S SCARY. -Scary?!
-（但是我會害怕） -“害怕”？
It's not scary.
沒什麼好怕的啦
Tadano will be there too.
有我和只野同學陪妳啊
I'm going too?
我也要去嗎？
Of course.
那還用說
Is that alright?
這樣好嗎？
Guys and girls shopping together…
我一個男生陪女生買衣服
All that changing of clothes…
可能還會試穿衣服
Look, Komi's conflicted!
看吧，古見同學也左右為難
I probably shouldn't--
我還是不要去…
You need to be her interpreter.
不行，一定要有翻譯隨行 不然我會很困擾的
-For me. -Oh, right.
-我需要 -喔，對喔
Can I invite someone else too?
我可以找別人一起去嗎？
NOD
（點頭）
-Agari! -Yes!
-上理！ -是！
Do you want to go shopping today?
今天要不要一起去買衣服？
Shopping?
買衣服？
Walkies for your dog?
是要帶狗去散步嗎？
I-I'd love to! I'll go!
好開心，我要去！
It's not a walkie.
不是去散步喔
First we'll walk around…
那我們先逛一圈…
Komi!
古見同學！
What a coincidence!
天啊，怎麼這麼巧啊？
It doesn't smell like a coincidence!
感覺不是偶然遇到！
Is everyone shopping? Can I join you?
你們是來買東西嗎？真好 我可以加入你們嗎？
Did you follow us?
妳一路在跟蹤我們？
What are you talking about, Najimi?
你在說什麼？馴染
Oh, nothing.
不，沒事
Hey, Komi.
古見同學，我問妳
What sort of clothes do you like?
妳喜歡什麼樣的衣服啊？
You have regular clothes, don't you?
妳應該有一些便服吧？
What style are they?
大多是什麼風格呢？
Yeah!
對啊！
I DON'T KNOW. MY MOM BUYS THEM.
（都是媽媽幫我買 我不太清楚）
Your mom?!
“媽媽”？
I KNOW I NEED SOME CLOTHES, BUT I HAVE NOTHING TO WEAR SHOPPING.
（我常在想需要買些外出服 但我沒有可以穿去服飾店的衣服）
I know the feeling!
我懂！
Alright, let's have a contest to choose clothes for Komi!
好，現在就來舉辦“讓古見同學穿上 自己所選的衣服之穿搭大對決”！
BAM
（氣勢磅礴）
A contest to choose clothes for Komi to wear?!
讓古見同學穿上 自己所選的衣服之穿搭大對決？
The rules are simple. Choose an outfit worth 10,000 yen or less.
比賽規則很簡單，預算一萬圓 將想讓古見同學穿上的衣服拿過來
She tries them on and we score them. The highest score wins!
然後讓她試穿，大家再一起打分數 最後買下分數最高的那套就行了！
I'm itching to start.
我迫不及待了
I-I'll do my best to get Komi to choose me!
我會努力讓古見同學 選我的那套衣服！
Can't we choose togeth--
大家一起挑選不就好了…
Alright, ready, go!
那麼比賽開始！
-Wow, what a pretty mannequin. -It's so realistic!
-那個假人模特兒好漂亮 -做得好像真的
Komi is mistaken for a mannequin.
古見同學被人誤以為是假人模特兒
It's time!
讓各位久等了！
Komi has finished changing!
古見同學剛剛換好了衣服！
Let's see her outfit!
馬上請她出來吧！
Komi!
古見同學！
-Komi? Can you come out? -TOO SHY TO SHOW THEM.
-古見同學？妳可以出來嗎？ -（古見同學因害羞而拉著布簾）
NAJIMI'S CHOICE
（馴染嚴選）
PUMPS 1,280 YEN DRESS 7,980 YEN
（平底鞋1280圓 旗袍7980圓）
HAIR ELASTIC 300 YEN
（髮圈300圓）
Can't get better than a cheongsam!
穿旗袍果然最讚啦！
You just wanted to see her in one.
你只是想讓她穿穿看吧？
Najimi Osana, 34 points.
長名馴染，總分34分
YAMAI'S CHOICE
（山井嚴選）
Next is Yamai's choice!
接下來是山井選的！
Easily exceeded the 10,000 yen limit!
大幅地超過了一萬圓！
Huh? Price?
什麼？價錢？
It's alright! I'll buy it for you!
沒問題啦，我買給她！
So flippant.
這份愛太沉重了啦
Disqualified for breaking the rules.
山井戀因違規遭到淘汰
AGARI'S CHOICE
（上理嚴選）
SHOES 2,980 YEN JEANS 4,980 YEN
（鞋子2980圓 牛仔褲4980圓）
T-SHIRT 1,980 YEN
（T恤1980圓）
Tacky!
好土！
TOTAL: 18 POINTS
（總分18分）
Huh? Isn't it cute?
奇怪，難道不可愛嗎？
Uh… This is just, um…
那個…
I don't know anything about women's fashion.
我不太懂女生的衣服潮流
I just chose whatever.
所以只是隨便選選
It's not like… I'm into girls like this or anything.
並不是說我喜歡穿這樣的女生…
Enough with the virgin excuses. Hurry up!
處男的藉口就免了，快拿給她穿啊
Alright.
好的
Here you go.
那就麻煩妳了
Finally, the last entry! Bring on Tadano's choice!
最後一套 來看看只野同學嚴選的衣服！
SANDALS 1,980 YEN DRESS 4,980 YEN
（涼鞋1980圓 連衣裙4980圓）
Wow, this is it.
哇，就是這件了
How does Komi like it?
那麼古見同學的反應如何？
SLIDE
（伸出）
Hooray!
太好了！
Total, 50 points.
總分50分
Komi bought Tadano's choice!
古見同學買了只野同學嚴選的衣服
Huh? You want to do it again?
奇怪，你還要再來一次嗎？
My last one was a joke.
剛才那是開玩笑
MISSION 18 "IT'S JUST THE HAIR SALON."
（任務18 去髮廊）
SHE MADE UP HER MIND.
（她下定了決心）
My name is Kamiko Arai.
我的名字叫新井嘉美子
I just started working here!
剛成為這間髮廊的員工！
I'm eager to learn!
是不久前開始在這工作的年輕新人！
What are you doing?
妳在幹什麼？
This is my talented boss, Maki Karisu.
這位是才華洋溢的 美髮師雁巢真姬小姐
I admire her so much!
是我崇拜的前輩！
-If you're not busy, go clean outside. -Yes!
-新井，沒事做的話，去打掃店門前 -好的！
I'm new here,
我還是個新人
so I can only clean up and wash hair.
只能負責打掃和洗頭
But one day I'll be a charismatic hairstylist like Karisu.
但總有一天我也要成為 像雁巢小姐那樣的有才美髮師…
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Oh! A customer?
是客人嗎？
Surely she must be! Alright!
應該是吧？好！
Welcome! Come on in!
歡迎光臨，請進！
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
No? Just a passer-by?
奇怪，不是嗎？她只是路過嗎？
What should I do? This is so awkward!
怎麼辦？現在氣氛好尷尬 我搞砸了嗎？
Oh, it's Shoko.
喔，是硝子啊
You're here. Come on in.
妳來了啊，進來吧
She went in!
她進去了！
She was a customer after all!
她果然是客人！
Why didn't she come in when I said it?
為什麼我向她搭話的時候 她不願意進來呢？
Was my smile weird?
是因為我的笑容不夠真誠嗎？
Was I too aggressive?
是因為我太積極了嗎？
D-Do I smell?
還是說我有臭味？
No! That's just the difference between me and a pro!
不對，這就是我 和非凡美髮師的差別！
My boss is amazing!
不愧是前輩！
What was that?
嚇我一跳
It's been a while, Shoko.
硝子，好久不見
What would you like?
今天想要做什麼造型？
Alright, blonde and short.
好，剪成短髮再染成金色吧
SHAKE SHAKE
（搖頭）
Just kidding.
開玩笑的啦
The usual, right?
老樣子對吧？
She's so pretty.
那女孩長得好漂亮啊
Such straight, long hair…
一頭有光澤的亮麗直髮
It would be a waste to cut it.
都讓人捨不得剪了
My boss, too.
但不愧是前輩
She looks so pretty and dignified when she cuts.
剪髮的姿態凜然，莊重又美麗
The two together are like a painting.
這兩人宛如一幅畫啊
What are you doing, Arai?
新井，妳在幹什麼？
-Get back to work. -Yes, sorry.
-快去工作 -是，對不起
Feel free to read the…
這些請自由取閱…
Huh?
奇怪
She's sleeping.
她睡著了
She's so cute.
真可愛
She's just pretending to sleep.
她只是在裝睡
SO NOBODY TALKS TO HER
（避免別人對她說話）
That reminds me, Shoko. You're in high school now, right?
對了，硝子，妳已經是高中生了吧？
How's high school life?
高中生活怎麼樣啊？
F.
開…
Ah, as long as you're having fun.
這樣啊，開心就好
They can communicate with just one sound?
只要一個字就能聽懂她想說的話！
My boss is amazing!
不愧是非凡美髮師！
Arai, give her a shampoo.
新井，幫她洗頭
That's me! My job!
我的工作來了！
Yes ma'am!
好的！
I should chat with the customer too.
我也必須和客人多聊聊
I just started working here from April.
我是今年4月剛進來的新人
If I do anything wrong, just tell me!
如果有哪裡服務不周 請別客氣，要儘管說喔
How long have you been coming to this salon?
能請教您是從多久前 開始光顧這家髮廊的嗎？
Display my weakness while asking easy questions!
主動展示自己的弱點 然後問對方一個容易回答的問題
It's perfect!
太完美了！
POINT
（用手指示）
Huh? 12? Since you were 12?
嗯？“12”？從12歲起嗎？
She used the magazine to answer?
用雜誌來回答嗎？
What does it mean? Why did she answer by pointing at the magazine?
這是怎麼回事？ 她為什麼要指著雜誌來回答我？
She could just say, "Since I was 12."
她只要說一句“從12歲起”就行了啊
Maybe she didn't want to talk to me? Is that it?
難道說她不想跟我說話？是這樣嗎？
She wouldn't enter the shop either.
剛才她也不願意進來
What's wrong with me?
我是哪裡做得不好？
At this rate,
這樣下去
I'll never become a pro hairstylist!
我根本無法成為非凡美髮師啊！
Why… why?
為什麼？到底是為什麼？
THE WHOLE PROCESS IS FINISHED.
（所有流程結束）
Well? You like it?
如何？喜歡嗎？
I'm glad.
那就好
That's 4,800 yen exactly.
收您4800圓整
Here's your receipt.
這是您的收據
Thank you very much! Please come again!
謝謝您，歡迎再度光臨！
Ms. Karisu.
雁巢前輩
I thought that customer hated me.
我本來以為那位客人討厭我
Well, some people just don't like chatting at the salon.
有些人在髮廊是很怕被別人搭話的
OUR WAY TO SAY THANK YOU
（含謝謝對方的心情！）
-THANK YOU. -I see.
-（謝謝） -原來如此
THE NEXT DAY
（隔天）
Howdy, Komi!
古見同學，早安地斯山脈
K-Komi! G-Good m-m-morning!
古見同學，早安！
Looking good!
今天也很美！
Good morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
Did you cut your hair?
奇怪，妳是不是剪頭髮了？
No way! Did you really cut it?
不會吧！妳真的有剪嗎？
It hasn't changed.
完全沒變啊
I can't believe I missed a change in my master.
我居然沒看出主人的變化
How could I not notice?!
我怎麼沒注意到啊？
MISSION 19 "IT'S JUST AN UNSETTLING FEELING."
（任務19 心情鬱悶糾結）
People with social anxiety tend to do this.
有交流障礙症的人
They tend to overanalyze things they say and do
往往會在半夜想著 “為什麼自己當初要說出那句話？”
which keeps them up at night.
導致輾轉難眠
CONVERSATION WITH YAMAI
（與山井同學的對話）
Komi, do you have a favorite food?
妳有喜歡吃的配菜嗎？
I'll make it for you.
我下次做給妳吃
FRIED EGGS.
（日式煎蛋）
Fried eggs! Got it!
日式煎蛋是吧？交給我吧！
WAS I TOO SLOW?
（為何沒有迅速回答？）
AM I TOO BORING?
（不能回答得更有趣嗎？）
ARE EGGS CHILDISH?
（煎蛋會不會太孩子氣？）
CONVERSATION WITH NAJIMI
（與馴染的對話）
Let's play a game together!
過來一起玩遊戲吧！
O… OKAY!
好！
Yay!
太好了！
WAS I BEING WEIRD?
（會不會覺得我興奮過頭？）
WHY THE CAT EARS?
（為何那時長出貓耳？）
The jacket got wet.
就把頭花弄溼了
I'm so clumsy.
我真是笨手笨腳
HEE-HEE
嘿嘿
WAS IT COLD?
（沒有傷風嗎？）
My book…? No, I don't think so.
沒有喔，當時沒有風
I MISUNDERSTOOD! JACKET = BOOK JACKET
（“頭花”聽成“頭髮” 對方以為“傷風”是“風”）
CONVERSATION WITH TADANO
（和只野同學的對話）
Sounds like you got the words mixed up.
妳把“頭花”聽成“頭髮” 她把“傷風”誤以為是指“風”
I-I'm sorry!
對不起！
I wasn't clear when I spoke!
都怪我講話不清不楚！
I bet they'll both feel bad afterwards.
她們兩個回去一定會反省這件事
I-It's alright!
別在意啦
It happens often.
這是常有的事
I used to think the country Turkey
我以前也把“不見不散”
was the same as turkey, the bird. Like how surreal is that?
聽成是“柬埔寨” 還以為是個國名呢
Like, y'know, "Hungary" and "hungry".
還有像是“主打歌”聽成“豬大哥”
Uh, yeah.
就像這樣
MISSION 20 "IT'S JUST A STUDY GROUP."
（任務20 考試前唸書）
I want to die.
我好想死
GLANCE
（偷瞄）
Maybe we should ask what's wrong.
這傢伙一副想說話的樣子
Oh, I don't actually want to die. Sorry.
啊，我沒有真的要去死啦，抱歉
Alright, I'll ask. Why?
我就姑且問問吧，為什麼？
Why? Did you just say "Why"?
“為什麼？” 你剛剛是不是問我原因？
Alright. I'll tell you.
那我就告訴你吧！
Exams start next week! That's why!
因為下週就要考試了呀！
You hate exams, don't you.
對喔，我記得你很討厭考試
Yeah!
沒錯！
Paying attention in class is enough.
上課時讀書就足夠了
I want to have fun. Have fun…
好想玩，我好想玩啊…
Hey! Let's all study together!
對了，我們來一起在考試前唸書吧！
I'm not getting study vibes.
這傢伙顯然不想讀書啊
S-Study for exams?
要考試前唸書嗎？
G-Go ahead! Feel free!
請大家自由使用這裡！
I haven't been in a library for 15 years.
我有15年沒踏進圖書室了
So you've never been to one.
換句話說，你一次都沒踏進來過嘛
Well spotted, Tadano!
被你發現了，只野同學！
WHACK
（打）
Quiet in the library!
在圖書室請保持安靜！
Agari, who's that?
上理，那個人是誰啊？
That's Gorimi Senpai.
她是檎林美學姐啦
Gorimi?!
檎林美？
She hits noisy students with a paper fan.
太吵鬧就會被她用紙扇打
Three strikes and you're out.
被打三下就是三振出局，要出去
What a weird rule.
這是什麼規則？
TRASHBOY IS TRASH
（《勒瑟同學是垃圾》）
Look at thi--
你們看這個…
Quiet in the library.
在圖書室請保持安靜
That paper fan is the loudest.
紙扇打人的聲音才是最吵的吧
NAJIMI 2 STRIKES
（馴染二好球）
Isn't that…?
那是…
If you start doing that,
你再繼續做這種事
you'll die!
真的會死啊！
It's fun, Tadano.
好好玩喔，只野同學
Sheesh.
這傢伙
This procrastination is getting out of hand.
他是不是因為 太不想讀書，腦袋壞掉了？
REACH
（悄悄伸手）
Komi?!
古見同學？
RELIEF
（鬆一口氣）
Next is your turn, Tadano.
下一個輪到只野同學了
We're being watched! Very closely!
她在看我們，狠狠瞪著我們！
No, um, I'm…
不，我還是…
A-Alright.
那我就…
Quiet in the library!
在圖書室請保持安靜！
Three strikes. Najimi was out.
馴染三振出局，因此被趕出去
Gosh. I'm sorry.
真是抱歉
MY FIRST STRIKE. THAT WAS FUN.
（我是第一次被紙扇打 好有趣喔）
Fun?
有趣嗎？
I WANTED TO PLAY, TOO.
（其實我也很想玩）
Ah, to tell you the truth, me too.
不瞞妳說，其實我也是
THEY LEFT.
（三人都出去了）
Let's join Najimi.
那我們去找馴染吧
Summer vacation! Hooray!
放暑假了，萬歲！
Pretty smart for someone who hates studying.
這傢伙不愛讀書，但頭腦很好
You did great, Komi.
古見同學，妳考得很好耶，好厲害
I lost at everything!
我全都輸了！
SHOKO KOMI MAKERU YADANO
（古見硝子 矢田野真華留）
MISSION 21 "IT'S JUST SUMMER BREAK."
（任務21 是暑假）
Komi hasn't gone outside since summer vacation started.
古見同學放暑假後，外出次數為零
FINISHED ALL HER HOMEWORK
（暑假作業全寫完了）
FEELING NERVOUS ABOUT GOING OUT
（因為自己都不出門 開始感到有些不安）
HOW TO INVITE A FRIEND OUT
（邀朋友出去玩的場合）
OKAY!
（下定決心！）
KOMI CAN'T PRESS THE CALL BUTTON.
（古見同學還是沒勇氣按下通話鍵）
I'm bored.
好閒啊
I want to go hang out with someone.
好想找人出去玩
Komi…
古見同學…
No, no, no…
不行…
Ew. What are you doing?
你幹嘛啊？好噁心
POPSICLE
（冰棒）
No way, I can't call her.
不行啦，我不方便去邀她啦
It's just, like…
感覺好像怪怪的
But with Komi…
可是古見同學
All week she must've wanted to call her friends and couldn't.
這禮拜可能想找朋友出去玩 卻一直沒勇氣開口
So she just did all her summer homework.
於是她就想來寫暑假作業
But now she's done and bored.
可是都寫完了，因此無事可做
Probably trembling and staring at her phone.
可能邊發抖邊瞪著手機吧
-No, no, no… -Hitohito?
-不… -哥哥，你還好嗎？
But on the off chance…
可是萬一…
I could call and check.
還是打個電話確認吧
But no…
不，可是…
SHOCK
（嚇到）
Mom, I think Hitohito might be sick.
媽媽，哥哥他好像生病了
KOMI MADE UP HER MIND AND CALLED TADANO.
（古見同學下定決心 打電話給只野同學）
Oh, hello, Komi?
喂？古見同學嗎？
It's everyone's childhood friend, Najimi Osana!
我是大家的兒時玩伴，長名馴染
Let's go to the pool tomorrow!
明天要不要去游泳池？
I invited Tadano and he said okay.
我剛剛邀了只野同學，他答應了
How about you, Komi?
妳要不要去？
Komi, can you hear me?
奇怪，妳有聽見嗎？
Hello? Hello?
喂？
I…
我…
I'll go.
我要去
Yay!
太好了！
See you tomorrow at 12 at Yomikiri Land Station!
那明天12點在讀切樂園站前集合
Bye!
拜拜！
FIST PUMP
（握拳）
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：馬慈光